Guide to the Allison H. Dean Papers 1920-1990
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Allison H. Dean Papers
1920-1990
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Coll 198
Dean, Allison H., 1897-
1.5 cubic feet 5 document cases
Papers of a real estate developer, architect, and amateur writer of Portland, Oregon, active in 1920s through the 1950s. Includes biographical materials, correspondence, and drafts of fiction and poetry.
Biographical Note
Born in Scituate Harbor, Massachusetts, on February 2, 1897, Allison H. Dean spent his childhood on the prairies of Saskatchewan, Canada, served in the Royal Air Force, and moved to Portland, Oregon in the mid-1920s to work as a real estate developer and architectural designer. He was a pioneer in the pre-fabricated homes industry starting in the 1940s. As an amateur actor and singer, he was active in local theater productions. He was a writer, working on poetry, autobiographical works, novels, short stories, and articles related to real estate beginning in the1930s. Some writings had success, but most went unpublished.
The collection consists of 5 boxes of material related to both Dean’s professional work in real estate and his endeavors in theater and writing. The collection contains personal and professional correspondence, newspaper and magazine clippings, original architectural drawings, theater programs, unpublished manuscripts, accounting records, photographs, and the collected writings of Queene B. Ryan (1891-1973), a friend of Dean’s.
The collection is arranged in the following series:
Series A: Biographical
Series B: Correspondence
Series C: Writings
Series D: Photograph
The collection is open to the public.
Acquired 2008, Library Accession 26550.
A collection of Allison H. Dean's photographs, including images of houses and house designs, in designated Org. Lot 187; and an oral history with Dean is designated SR 9057 -- both in the Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Dean, Allison H., 1897- --Archives; Ryan, Queene B.
Portland (Or.)--Biography; Portland (Or.)--Buildings, structures, etc.
Authors--Oregon.; Prefabricated houses--Design and construction--Oregon--Portland.; Real estate agents--Oregon--Portland.; Theater--Oregon--Portland--History.
Architecture; City and Town Life; Oregon; Literature; Portland
Letters (correspondence); Manuscripts (for publication); Poems
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Biographical materials, 1924-1977; Series A
  - Career materials, 1938-1969 (Box-folder 1/1)
    Documents regarding new developments in prefabricated homes, circa 1941-1942
    Documents regarding contracting to government
    Hand drawn rough architectural plans for residences
    Fliers for “America’s first low cost factory home, completely furnished and equipped, completely factory built.”
    Documents for Office of Emergency Management, 1942
    Federal Housing Administration booklet, “Rental housing for investment.” 1938
    Materials from National Institute of Real Estate Brokers
    Photograph of a pre-fabricated home being loaded onto a truck. Caption reads “Tuesday 10 AM. June 24/41, LOADING, Factory Built and Furnished, LOW Cost Union Built. HAUL-A-WAY HOME, Patents Pending, Allison H. Dean, Allison Dean. Investor and Sales Agent, Drake Wyman & Voss Inc. Fabricators, 208 N. Broadway Portland Oregon At 9216”
    List of companies in manufactured home business, with addresses and notes.
    Publication, The Canadian Realtor, October 1968, volume 14, number 10
    Letter from National Institute of Real Estate Brokers for acceptance of an article for publication in Real Estate Today publication, 1969
  - Career materials, 1941-1977 (Box-folder 1/2)
    Document, “Declaration of reservations, restrictions, conditions and easements affecting the plat of dean’s park subdivision” 1977
    Blank form from Executive Office of the President, Office for Emergency Management
    Envelope with documents, blueprints, plans, and photo related to land development 1941
    Document, “Guest list – Georgia-Pacific Reception and Dinner – Arlington Club– July 19, 1955”
    Drawings of architectural feature
    Handwritten notes, accounting or blank
    Drawings of architectural plans
    1967 zip code informational card
    Drawing, portrait sketch
    Clipping of address for Torrey & Dean, Inc., Realtors, 409 U.S. Bank Bldg., Portland, Oregon
  - Account Book, 1931-1947 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Clippings, 1931-1965 (Box-folder 1/4)
    National real estate journal 12/21/1931 volume 32, number 26
    National Real Estate Journal 1/5/1931 volume 32, number 1
    Product documentation, “Bruning Transparent Plastic Scales, Their USE and CARE”
    Pamphlet, “Guideposts, a practical guide to successful living” April, 1965
    Miscellaneous collected clippings related to residential architecture and interior design, from popular color magazines circa 1955-1964
    Sunday Oregonian 7/20/1958 advertising insert for Raleighwood development
    Blue print magazine insert by Ellis Leigh/designer and Emil a.Schmidlin/architect, east orange new jersey, magazine clipping
  - Clippings, 1930-1966 (Box-folder 1/5)
    Leaflet, “the Portland Realtor” 3/18/1959 volume 39, number 11
    Local newspaper clippings related to theater, circa 1930
    Page from Sunday Oregonian August 7, 1966
    1 stamp sized photo of Allison H. Dean, and duplicate in original leaflet from which it was taken
  - Clippings, circa 1958-1959 (Box-folder 1/6)
    Sunday Oregonian clippings relating to taxation and Dr. John F. Sly, circa 1958-1959
    Clipping of advertisement with architectural plan image and handwritten notes
    Columbia Records album liner
  - Queene B. Ryan collection, circa 1920-1973 (Box-folder 1/7)
    Photograph, portrait of Queene Bell Ryan, 1891-1973, on horse
    Clipping of obituary
    Handwritten 2 page biographical note for Queen B. Ryan, draft for published obituary
    Collected poems of Queene B. Ryan
  - Programs of theater productions, circa 1930-1931 (Box-folder 1/8)
    1 handwritten note mounted on a sheet of 81/2 x 11” paper with handwritten caption, signature of actress Pauline Friedrich, 1930-12-6
    Program from theater production, “The Green Goddess”, Art Theatre Players, circa 1930
    program from theater production, “Officer 666”, Portland Civic Theater, circa 1930
    program from theater production, “A Doll’s House”, Portland Civic Theater, circa 1931
    program from theater production, “The Unseen Guest”, Portland Civic Theater, circa 1930
    program from theater production, “Dear Brutus”, Portland Civic Theater, circa 1930
    publication of Dufwin theater, “The Showgoer”, circa 1930
- Correspondence, 1930-1990; Series B
  - General, primarily with publishers, 1962-1990 (Box-folder 1/9)
    Letters from publishers and literary agents regarding Dean’s manuscript submissions. circa 1962-1967
    Letter to Mary Chambers Jones of rejection for publication of Dean manuscript, 1990
  - Publishers, 1930-1968 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Stout, Rex, 1974 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Willkie, Wendell, 1944 (Box-folder 1/12)
- Writings, 1935-1976; Series C
  - Professional documents, article manuscript, 1961-1976 (Box-folder 2/1)
    Author’s Guild letter, 1972
    “Guide to the author’s guild trade book contract” 1972
    Author’s Guild trade book contract 1972
    Pamphlet, “What is a literary agent?”
    Publication, “The Writer” June 1975
    Pamphlet, “International Novel Award”
    Oregonian clipping, 1961-8-24
    List of publishing houses, 1976
    Miscellaneous fragments
    Typrewritten manuscript, “on dramatic living rooms:”
    handwritten manuscripts
    copies of calligraphed prayer
  - Novel, “Singer in the Temple, circa 1955 (Box-folder 2/2-2/6)
  - Novel, “Singer in the Temple, circa 1955 (Box-folder 3/1-3/4)
  - Political writings and publications, 1935 (Box-folder 3/5)
    Handwritten notes for a debate at Barbur Blvd Realty Board, 1935
    Typewritten document on subject of taxation
    Publication, “Oregon Voter” 1965-11-27
    Publication, “Oregon Voter” 1965-11-13
    Publication, “Oregon Voter” 1965-11-20
  - Short stories
    - “A Matter of Experience”, undated (Box-folder 4/1)
    - “Angus Rusk”, undated (Box-folder 4/2)
    - “Betting Blacksmith”, 1964-1-5 (Box-folder 4/3)
      Published in Sunday Empire, The Magazine of the Denver Post, January 5, 1964
    - “Businessman's Bible”, undated (Box-folder 4/4)
    - “Concrete Bulls”, 1960 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - “Dear Teacher”, undated (Box-folder 4/6)
    - “Depends on How You Say It”, undated (Box-folder 4/7)
    - “Flacon of Parfum”, undated (Box-folder 4/8)
    - “From the Road to the River”, undated (Box-folder 4/9)
    - “From the Road to the River”, undated (Box-folder 4/10)
    - “From Under a Bushel”, undated (Box-folder 4/11)
    - “Harvest Idyll”, undated (Box-folder 5/1)
    - “John McCormack and I”, undated (Box-folder 5/2)
    - “Jones For Joyous Service”, undated (Box-folder 5/3)
    - “Life of a Salesman”, undated (Box-folder 5/4)
    - “Lunch Hour”, 1965 (Box-folder 5/5)
    - “Man Who Saw God”, 1964 (Box-folder 5/6)
    - “Moonlight Sonata”, undated (Box-folder 5/7)
    - “My Garden”, undated (Box-folder 5/8)
    - “My Sod Home on the Prairie”, 1965-5-16 (Box-folder 5/9)
      Published in Sunday Empire, The Magazine of the Denver Post, May 16, 1965
    - “Ninety-Eight Cents”, undated (Box-folder 5/10)
    - “Organist”, undated (Box-folder 5/11)
    - “Prairie Boy”, undated (Box-folder 5/12)
      2 copies of self-published booklet, including biographical sketch, a photo of Dean, and the writings, “Prairie Boy”, “My Sod Home on the Prairie”, “the Betting Blacksmith”, “Sports Day”, “The Stopping House”, “Brains”, “The Hate Harvest”, “The Moonlight Sonata”.
      Typed drafts for “Prairie Boy”
    - “Second Chance”, undated (Box-folder 5/13)
    - “Soddy”, undated (Box-folder 5/14)
    - “Sports Day”, undated (Box-folder 5/15)
    - “They Smiled”, undated (Box-folder 5/16)
  - Speeches, undated (Box-folder 5/17)
- Photograph, 1950; Series D (Box-folder 5/18)
  Photograph of two women, tentatively identified as Dean’s daughters.